Have you ever wondered if you see the same colours as other people?
你是否曾好奇过，自己看到的颜色和别人看到的是不是一样的？
Most people know what blue is when they see it.
大多数人看到蓝色时都能认出来，它是大海、天空和蓝宝石的颜色。
It’s the colour of sea, sky and sapphires.
人们之所以会把这种颜色叫做“蓝色”，是因为他们学过这个词，并且将这个词和自己看到的事物联系在了一起。
They see the colour and call it ‘blue’ because they were taught the word and associated it with what they saw.
但你怎么知道，自己眼中的蓝色，不会是别人眼中的红色呢？
But how do you know what you see as blue isn’t someone else’s red, and vice versa?
反之亦然。
The ability to perceive different colours is down to receptors in our eyes known as cones.
感知不同颜色的能力，取决于我们眼睛里一种叫做视锥细胞的感受器。
Light waves hit these receptors and they react depending on which colour the light is, sending signals to the brain.
光波照射到这些感受器上时，感受器会根据光的颜色产生不同反应，并向大脑发送信号。
The brain then decodes these signals to determine which colour light the eyes are receiving.
随后大脑会解码这些信号，从而判断眼睛接收到的光是什么颜色。
Some people’s receptors are more developed than others.
有些人的感受器发育得比其他人更好。
People with weaker receptors usually have colour blindness.
感受器功能较弱的人通常会患有色盲。
The inability of the receptor to interpret the light waves correctly means that some people cannot distinguish between different shades of a colour.
感受器无法正确解读光波，就意味着这些人无法区分同一种颜色的不同深浅色调。
Those with more enhanced receptors can see more shades of one colour, which is the first way in which people may see colours differently from each other.
感受器功能更强的人，能看到同一种颜色更多的色调变化，这是人与人之间颜色感知存在差异的第一个原因。
We sometimes hear people having an argument about whether something is dark blue or black. It might be because one person has stronger receptors to interpret the light than another.
我们有时会听到人们争论某样东西到底是深蓝色还是黑色，这很可能是因为其中一个人解读光线的感受器功能比另一个人更强。
In the past, most scientists would argue that everyone saw colours in the same way.
过去，大多数科学家都认为，所有人看到的颜色都是一样的。
However, research was conducted on monkeys, in which they were injected with a virus affecting their receptors. This enabled them to distinguish more colours than usual and brought an intriguing revelation.
然而，一项针对猴子的研究得出了一个有趣的新发现——研究人员给猴子注射了一种会影响其感受器的病毒，让它们能比平时分辨出更多颜色。
Normally monkeys can only see in blue and green, but the virus allowed monkeys to see red.
通常情况下，猴子只能看到蓝色和绿色，而这种病毒让它们看到了红色。
The neurons in their brains spontaneously adapted to be able to understand new colours, which might mean the neurons in our brains are not hardwired to automatically understand which colour is which.
猴子大脑中的神经元自发适应了新的颜色信息，这或许意味着，我们大脑中的神经元并非天生就会自动识别各种颜色。
This implies that our brains and neurons may adapt depending on our stimulus during the developmental phase.
这表明，在发育阶段，我们的大脑和神经元可能会根据外界刺激发生适应性变化。
Colour could be a very personal experience, unique to everyone.
因此，颜色感知可能是一种非常个人化的体验，因人而异，独一无二。
So, the next time you talk about your favourite colour, just remember if yours is blue and your friend says red, you might actually be thinking about the same colour.
所以下次你和别人聊起自己最喜欢的颜色时，不妨想一想：如果你喜欢的是蓝色，而你的朋友喜欢的是红色，你们俩说的也许其实是同一种颜色。
What if everyone in the world has the same favourite colour, but just calls it different names?
要是全世界的人最喜欢的都是同一种颜色，只是叫法不同，那会怎么样呢？